Guide to the William Julius Mickle Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Julius Mickle papers
1753-1825
OSB MSS 159
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The William Julius Mickle Papers document aspects of the literary and naval careers of William Julius Mickle. The collection includes correspondence from literary figures such as William Ballantyne, William Bowles, David Garrick, Francis Gentleman, Isaac Reed, and John Sim, and from family friend and naval patron Commodore George Johnstone; manuscripts of several works by Mickle, including The Concubine and The Death of Socrates; and papers relating to Mickle's service as prize agent for Johnstone's naval squadron.
Mickle, William Julius, 1735-1788
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by James Marshall Osborn from Sotheby's (21 May 1968 sale), 1968. Bequest of James Marshall Osborn, 1976.
Custodial History
From the collection of T. M. Ellis.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Julius Mickle,1734 or 1735-1788.
William Julius Mickle (1734 or 1735-1788), was born William Meikle in Scotland and inherited his father's Edinburgh brewery in 1757. After it failed financially in 1763, Mickle secretly moved to London, changed the spelling of his last name, and embarked on a literary career. He was corrector for the Clarendon Press, Oxford, from 1765 to 1772. Mickle's first success was the neo-Spenserian poem The Concubine (1767).
From 1772 until 1779 he lived with a patron, Robert Tomkins of Forest Hill, and attempted to earn his living solely as an author. He repeatedly rewrote his verse tragedy, The Seige of Marseilles, in the hopes of seeing it performed, but the London theater managers repeatedly refused to stage it. His other ambitious project was more successful: his verse translation of Luís de Camões's epic poem Os Lusíadas (1572) was published by subscription in 1776 as The Lusiad, or, The Discovery of India. While Mickle's command of Portuguese was questionable, the work earned him almost a thousand pounds and remained the standard translation of this national epic for almost a century.
Mickle, however, was still burdened with old debts, and in 1779 his patron Commodore George Johnstone appointed him purser of the HMS Brilliant. Johnstone's squadron was stationed in Portugal, and the Portguese welcomed the translator of their national poet, electing Mickle to the Academia Reale. His naval career was a success; in 1780 he was appointed prize agent for the squadron, which improved his fortunes enough for him to marry Mary Tomkins, daughter of Robert Tomkins, in 1782. The couple moved to Wheatley, Oxfordshire, where Mickle spent much time revising his works. He died after a short illness in 1788 and was survived by his wife and his son, Charles Julius Mickle.
Scope and Contents
The William Julius Mickle Papers document aspects of the literary and naval careers of William Julius Mickle. The collection includes correspondence from literary figures including William Ballantyne, William Bowles, David Garrick, Francis Gentleman, Isaac Reed, and John Sim, as well as from family friend and naval patron Commodore George Johnstone; manuscripts of several works by Mickle, including The Concubine and The Death of Socrates; and papers relating to Mickle's service as prize agent for Johnstone's naval squadron in the early 1780s.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence, 1753-1825. II. Writings, 1762-1774. III. Naval Papers, 1780-1789.
Authors, English -- 18th century; English drama -- 18th century; English poetry -- 18th century; Prizes (Property captured at sea) -- Great Britain; Ballantyne, William; Bowles, William, 1705-1780; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; Gentleman, Francis, 1728-1784; Johnstone, George, 1730-1787; Lyttelton, George Lyttelton, Baron, 1709-1773; Magalhães, João Jacinto de, 1722-1790; Mickle, William Julius, 1735-1788; Reed, Isaac, 1742-1807; Brilliant (Ship); Great Britain. Royal Navy -- Officers
- Correspondence, 1753-1825; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically arranged by correspondent. Letters from Mickle to other recipients are filed under "Mickle, William Julius."
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters received by William Julius Mickle, mostly concerning literary matters. Major correspondents include the authors William Bowles, Francis Gentleman, David Price, and the book collector and scholar Isaac Reed. Letters from William Ballantyne and João Jacinto Magalhães discuss Mickle's translation of Os Lusiadas (The Luciad). An undated letter by David Garrick offers the young poet advice, while a 1769 letter contains criticism of The Siege of Marseilles.
  The letters of Commodore George Johnstone contain personal and family news as well as information relating to Mickle's service in the Royal Navy. Some of the letters by Mickle, located in folders 89-105, also concern naval affairs and prize money.
  - Anderson, Alexander, 1780-1781 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, John, 1767-1769 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Armstrong, - (Mr.), 1788 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arthur, D., [1780?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ashe, Robert Hoadley, 1778 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ballantyne, William, 1773-1805 (Box 1, Folder 6-11)
  - Balmain, J., 1780 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Barclay, James, 1768 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Barnard, Frederick Augusta, 1778 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bathurst, Henry, Bishop of Norwich, 1785-1806 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Bew, John, 1777-1782 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Birt, Richard, 1788 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Blake, Joshua, 1781 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bowles, William (1755-1826), 1778-1786 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Braithwaite, D., 1779-1780 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brooks, William, 1772 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bryer, William, 1783-1787 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bucknay, Andrew, 1755 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Caldecott, Thomas, 1772-1783, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Campbell, Coll, 1781 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Campbell, Mrs. Hannah, 1781 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Charters, Thomas, 1789 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cleghorn, William, 1781-1785 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correa, Jose, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Crichton, William, 1780 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fenton, Richard (1747-1821), 1773 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ford, Mrs. M., 1784-1788 (Box 1, Folder 36-38)
  - Garrick, David (1717-1779), 1769 November 29, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gentleman, Francis (1728-1784), 1764-1767 (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Good, William (d. 1776), 1763-1764 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Graeme, (Captain) Alex, 1781 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hadow, James F., 1783 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Harmen, (John?), 1781 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Hartwell, (Brod?), 1781 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Hollist, Thomas, 1776 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Home, Rodman, 1781-1783 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hoola, John, no year, August 27 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hopper, Thomas, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Hudson, William, 1780-1784 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Innes, Alexander, 1782 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Ireland, James, 1768 February (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Irving, Matthew (b. 1714), 1783 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Jackson, P., 1783 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Jackson, William, 1782-1788 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Johnstone, Alexander (1727-1783), 1779 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Johnstone, (Commodore) George (1730-1787), 1773-1786 (Box 1, Folder 59-62)
  - Johnstone, John (1734-1795), 1787 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Johnstone, Walter, 1776-1778 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Langhome, John (1735-1779), 1765 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Lawson, James, 1781 February (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Lord, M., 1765 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Lyttelton, George (1709-1773), 1763-1765 (Box 1, Folder 68-69)
  - Lyttelton, Lord (verbatim copy of letters to and from), 1763 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - MacDonogh, Felix, 1785 (Box 2, Folder 71-72)
  - McLaurin, (Captain) John, 1785-1787 (Box 2, Folder 73-74)
  - Magalhães, João Jacinto (1722-1790), 1771-1780 (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
  - Maltby, Richard G., 1782 September 26 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Mayne, Edward and Mackenzie Chas, 1783 March 19 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Margetson, J., 1784 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Maxwell, John, 1778 July 27 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Mayne, Thomas, 1779 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - McDowall, Charles, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 83-84)
  - Meikle, Alexander and Thomas, 1751 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Meikle, Alexander (d. 1757), 1753 November 22 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Mickle, Charles (?-1768), 1762 November 1 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Mickle, Thomas, 1776-1789 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Mickle, William Julius (1735-1788), 1762-1788, undated (Box 2, Folder 89-105)
  - Murdoch, John (1747-1824), 1766-1783 (Box 2, Folder 106-107)
  - Mickle, Thomas, 1776-1789 (Box 2, Folder 108-109)
  - Owen, David (1754-1829), 1779-1780, undated (Box 2, Folder 110-112)
  - Pasley, Charles, 1780, undated (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Pasley, Robert, 1780 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Piercy, Ed, 1784 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Prince, Daniel (d. 1790), 1765-1767 (Box 2, Folder 116-119)
  - Pulteney, Sir William, 5th Bar. (1729-1805), 1781 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Raffles, Sir Thomas Stamford (1781-1826), 1825 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Rebello, D. Alves, 1777-1782 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Reed, Isaac (1742-1807), 1772-1787, undated (Box 2, Folder 123-130)
  - Robins, William, 1783 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Rodney, George Brydges Rodney, 1st baron (1719-1792), 1788 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Rutherford, W., undated (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Sim, John (1746-1824), 1783-1808, undated (Box 2, Folder 134-138)
  - Stephens, William, 1781 December 19 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Stephens, William and John James, 1760-1786 (Box 2, Folder 140-141)
  - Walker, William, 1763-1768 (Box 2, Folder 142-145)
  - Walpole, Robert (1736-1810), 1780 (Box 2, Folder 146-147)
  - Warton, Joseph (1722-1800), 1771 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - West, James (1704-1772), 1769 June 27 (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - Wheeler, William, 1822 July 8 (Box 2, Folder 150)
  - Whiteley, W., 1788 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Willoughby, Dobson, 1787 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - Wright, Thomas (d. 1797), 1769, undated (Box 2, Folder 153-155)
  - Unidentified, 1757 (Box 2, Folder 156)
- Writings, 1762-1774; Series II; 0.41; (1 box)
  Alphabetically arranged by title of work, with untitled material at the end.
  Contents include drafts of The Concubine and The Death of Socrates. The devotional essays at the end of the series are mostly incomplete.
  - The Concubine, [circa 1767] (Box 3, Folder 157)
    Notebook also includes draft of Count Chateaubriant, an early version of The Siege of Marseilles.
  - The Death of Socrates, a Masque: holograph, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 158)
  - Providence: holograph draft poem, 1762 (Box 3, Folder 159)
  - The Siege of Marseilles: proof fragment, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - Untitled devotional essays, undated (Box 3, Folder 161)
- Naval Papers, 1780-1789,undated; Series III
  Naval Papers includes letters of petition for prize money addressed to Mickle in his capacity as prize agent for Commodore Johnstone's squadron; copies of notes and memoranda; and a drawing of the squadron at anchor in a bay.
  - Naval papers, 1780-1784, undated (Box 3, Folder 162)